<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true picture and relation of Prince Henry his noble and vertuous disposition containing certaine observations and proofes of his towardly and notable inclination to vertue, of the pregnancie of his wit, farre above his age, comprehended in sundry of his witty and pleasant speaches. By W.H. With the true relation of the sicknesse and death of the same most illustrious prince, vvith the opening of his body. Written by a famous doctor of physick in French, and newly translated into English.</title>
            <author>W. H., fl. 1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02447</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103592</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839342</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839342</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3751</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02447)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3751)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1602:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true picture and relation of Prince Henry his noble and vertuous disposition containing certaine observations and proofes of his towardly and notable inclination to vertue, of the pregnancie of his wit, farre above his age, comprehended in sundry of his witty and pleasant speaches. By W.H. With the true relation of the sicknesse and death of the same most illustrious prince, vvith the opening of his body. Written by a famous doctor of physick in French, and newly translated into English.</title>
                  <author>W. H., fl. 1634.</author>
                  <author>Haydone, William.</author>
                  <author>Mayerne, Théodore Turquet de, Sir, 1573-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by VVilliam Christian,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Leyden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.H. = William Haydone?.</note>
                  <note>A famous doctor of physick = Sir Théodore Turquet de Mayerne.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3751:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRVE PICTVRE <hi>AND RELATION</hi> OF PRINCE HENRY His Noble and Vertuous diſpoſition, <hi>CONTAINING</hi> Certaine Obſervations and Proofes of his towardly and notable Inclination to Vertue, of the Pregnancie of his Wit, farre above his Age, comprehended in ſundry of his witty and pleaſant Speaches.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the true Relation of the Sickneſſe and Death of the ſame most illustrious Prince, vvith the opening of his Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by a famous Doctor of Phyſick in French, and newly tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LEYDEN, Printed by <hi>VVilliam Chriſtian.</hi> 1634.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3751:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <p>
               <hi>Conſecrated and Dedicated</hi> TO THE MOST HIGH AND PEERELES PRINCESSE <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> PRINCESSE OF GREAT BRITAINE, QVEENE OF BOHEMIA, PRIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CESSE PALATINE, DV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHESSE OF BAVA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIA, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>BY</hi> HER MAIESTIES MOST AFFECTIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NED AND BOVND IN ALL HVMBLE DVTY <hi>VV. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3751:2"/>
            <head>THE TRVE PICTVRE AND <hi>RELATION OF PRINCE</hi> HENRY His Noble and Vertuous diſpoſition, <hi>Containing</hi> Certaine Obſervations and Proofes of his <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and notable inclination to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue, of the preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of his Wit farre above his Age, comprehended in ſundry of his vvitty and pleaſant ſpeeches.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong ſo many thouſand wicked and corrupt people that liue diſperſed abroad through the world, there is one ſorte, if not worſer then others, yet at leaſt is ſuch as ought to be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked among thoſe that are manifeſtly wicked before the world; namely, ſuch as are ingrate, and among them a great number of thoſe that liue in the courts of great Princes and Lords, and by all poſſible meanes doe labour to attaine to riches, honour, and preferment, through the helpe and fauour of theſe great ones, whom (whilſt they are yet aliue) they doe reuerence, honour, and extoll with high and extrauagant prayſes, placing them (as it were) among the celeſtiall powers. But thoſe great perſons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3751:3"/>being once dead, and conſequently their hope to gaine or profit any more by them hauing now failed them, they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get within a ſhort time their benefactors, without ſpeaking almoſt of them any more, or at leaſt not making any hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mention of them, to the end that they might perpetuate their memorie and fame to their poſteritie, according as they had juſtly deſerued at their hands whileſt they liued. As for my ſelfe, hauing once had the honour to bee one of the moſt illuſtrious Prince HENRY his ſervants, and acknowledging my ſelfe to be perpetually bound and addebted to his Highnes, ſo long as my ſoule and body ſhall be united together, and therefore being unwilling to be accounted among thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate, and as it were diſloyall perſons, I haue gathered and ſet downe (though ſomewhat rudelie and confuſedlie) theſe obſeruations following, which doe containe diuers of his merrie and notable ſpeeches, when he was yet of verie tender yeares, being infallible and certaine tokens of his great and unſpeakable vertues, and of his nature good in all perfection (if any ſuch was euer found in any Prince) which in the meane while ſhall ſerue for an abridgment of his life, untill ſuch time as ſome other ſhall write and ſet downe the ſame more amply, and in more high and delicate termes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, concerning his behauiour towards God and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, there hath alwayes bene obſerued in him rare tokens of a religious and vertuous diſpoſition; as namelie, in his deuote and reuerent manner of praying, and hearing of publicke Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and Sermons; in his perpetuall refraining from oathes, and all irreligious and laſciuious ſpeaches, in his reprouing and diſlyking of ſuch as haue been about him, for any unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent or vicious behauior. And chiefly, when they did ſweare or take the name of God in vaine. In ſo much that being yet but verie young, he tooke ſuch order, that none of his young
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3751:3"/>Gentlemen and Pages were taken with this offence. And if any had offended (which did fall out but ſeldome) he was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſome little piece of money, to be given to the poore. And for his owne part (which is more rare, and almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to great Princes) he did never ſweare all his lifetime.</p>
            <p>In his behauiour towards his Parents, he was alwayes du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and reſpectiue farre aboue his age, and the maner of other children: for ſince he was but two yeares old, he both knew and reſpected the King his father aboue all others, and neuer was wearie to be in his companie: albeit his Majeſtie with the tokens of his loue to him would ſometimes interlace ſharpe ſpeeches, and other demonſtrations of fatherlie ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; yea his affection to his Majeſtie did grow with his age, for being preſent on a time at a fall, which his Majeſtie had from his horſe, he bevvailed this miſchance (which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe was leſſe then it was feared to be) with tears and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches full of compaſſion and loue. And likewiſe the reſpect which he caried to them increaſed daylie, as by this example I ſhall breefly declare. His High. one day hauing come forth of <hi>S. Iames</hi> his houſe a little before ſupper, to walck in the Parck, hauing a great number of his Gentlemen with him, &amp; ſeeing the Kings Majeſtie a farre of returning from his walk, and comming towards him, with a verie ſmall companie, he was aſhamed, and looking about him commanded his follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers to depart and goe no further with him. Which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatelie they did, leauing him almoſt alone, and thus did he meet the King, not hauing paſt three or foure to attend and waite on him.</p>
            <p>The ſame reſpect likewiſe did hee carie to the Queene his Mother, as among manie other things he declared herein: for going often to viſit her, and to ſhew his humble and louing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3751:4"/>dutie towards her Majeſtie, and ſometimes ſhee being buſied, or otherwayes letted by her affaires, and for this cauſe not admitting him to her preſence (though inwardly with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe he might be diſpleaſed therewith) yet in ſhow did he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeeme to be any wayes diſcontended therewith, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned alvvayes to his lodging vvith great patience, after that he had vvaited a long time in vaine.</p>
            <p>His brotherly loue vvas likevviſe verie great, vvhich did euidently appeare one day, the King being at <hi>Otlands,</hi> and a falſe rumour being ſpred abroad, that the Kings Majeſtie vvas ſlaine, his H. and the Duke of <hi>York</hi> his brother, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then both at <hi>S. Iames</hi> his houſe, hee couered for that preſent time his exceſſiue ſorovv and griefe, vvhich he had conceaued invvardly, and called for the Duke his brother in great haſte, that hee might once ſee him in ſafetie vvith him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; &amp; thus vvent to Whitehall together to the Queen, who had ſent for the Prince lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before more then once: but he put off his going till he had his brother to goe along vvith him.</p>
            <p>And as for the Lady ELIZABETH his Siſter, hee loued her alvvayes ſo dearly, that hee deſired to ſee her alwayes by him. And (at leaſt) they did viſite each other once in tvvo dayes, if time and occaſion had ſerued, and that they had been any thing neare together. Othervvayes he did ſend often to inquire of her health, vvith diuers unfallible ſignes and tokens of his great loue &amp; affection tovvards them both.</p>
            <p>In his cariage tovwards other perſons, hee did behaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vvith ſuch due reſpect and diſcretion, as it is rare to be found in one of his ranke and age.</p>
            <p>He vvas brought op even from his cradle, by an ancient, vertuous and ſeuere Lady; to vvit, the olde Counteſſe of <hi>Marre,</hi> vvho kept all ſuch as vvere about him in avve: yet did
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3751:4"/>hee not onely reverence her, but alſo loue her moſt dearly.</p>
            <p>Towards the right honorable the Earle of <hi>Marre,</hi> ſonne to the ſaid Lady, who had the principall charge and cuſtodie of him, he alwayes ſhewed himſelfe moſt louing and duetifull, in ſo much as before his comming to Engeland, the Earle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering him in preſence of the Councell to the charge of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lordes appointed to vviate on him in his journey, hee ſuddainly imbracing the ſaid Earle bruſt foorth into teares: albeit hee was knowen to weepe as litle as any child what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Next his Parents, he was alwayes moſt loving to his Schoolemaiſter S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Adam Newton:</hi> notwithſtanding that the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Adam Newton</hi> did alwayes preferre his owne dutie, and his Highnes well doing before the pleaſing of his fancies.</p>
            <p>I need not record with what courteſie and diſcretion he behaued himſelfe to all others, ſeeing all that knew him doe witneſſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>The ſeeds and buddes of Princely Vertues haue appeared in him, euen from his moſt tender yeares. His naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Iuſtice did ſhew it ſelfe continually; in that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Pages and other young Gentelmen placed about him, he did moſt grace and fauour ſuch, as euen by men of greateſt judgement were thought to be of beſt behauiour and deſert, wherein alſo may be perceiued more judgement then is incident to the age of a child.</p>
            <p>His courage was alwayes ſeene in that he did weepe as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as any child. When hee was verie young hauing hurt both his hands with a fall, in ſuch ſort that they bledde: albeit the ſmart which he felt wrong from him ſome teares: yet did he riſe up in the meane time ſmyling, and as it were diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling his hurt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3751:5"/>At another time he was ſo hurt in the ſhin, as it was ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely cured in a moneth after: yet being then aſked whether any thing ailed him, he anſwered (nothing) and ran up and downe playing him as before.</p>
            <p>An other token of his courage was, that being verie young he tooke great delight in the ſound of Drummes and Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, yea and of his Pieces both ſmall and great, beeing ſhot neare to him.</p>
            <p>When he was ſcarcely ſeauen yeares of age, a boy of good courage almoſt a yeare older then his Highnes falling by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to buffets with him, and doing the worſt he could, his Highnes both had the upperhand of him when they were parted a ſunder, and loued the ſame boy euer after the better for his courage.</p>
            <p>It was a great token of temperance in him, that in his diet he was naturally moderate, and leſſe dainty then children uſe to be, yea he was eaſily perſuaded by ſuch, as either for their place about him, or for his opinion of their vertue and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had credit with him, to forbeare either meate or other thing, wherein he tooke greateſt delight.</p>
            <p>In patience he exceeded all others, as this hiſtorie follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing doth amply declare; Being at a certaine time at his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of <hi>Woodſtock,</hi> intending one day to ryde abroad a hunting betimes in the morning, and the time beeing come, and he ready for his Bootes, his Shoemaker by miſchance had made one of them too ſtrait, for which cauſe divers that ſtood by in the meane while checked him very ſharply, labouring with all to ſtirre up his Highnes againſt him: yet he would by no meanes ſo do, but verie coldly and mildly commanded him to go ſpeedily, and make it a litle vvyder. So he went forth leauing his Maiſter onely with one boote, who ſate thus in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3751:5"/>his chaire for the ſpace of an houre and more, waiting for his Shoemakers backcomming, and talking all the time merrilie with thoſe that were about him, which in the meane while did ſhew themſelves verie impatient, and would gladly haue had the Prince to be the like. At laſt, the Shoemaker ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing brought backe the Boote for his Highnes, not only did he not chide him, but contrariwiſe looked on him with a cherefull countenance, which made them all amaſed, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Shoemaker himſelfe; who expected nothing leſſe then ſuch a fauorable aſpect, and came all ſweating and trembling for feare (as he had verie good cauſe to do.) Did he not herein vanquiſh and ſurmount himſelfe?</p>
            <p>He promiſed nothing raſhly or unaduiſedly to any one: but if once hee had been induced to ingadge himſelfe any wayes, hee would be ſure to performe what once hee had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which by this example is manifeſt. One of his houſhold ſeruants, to whom he had promiſed a better place then that which he then poſſeſſed, and with time had forgotten the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me promiſe, and this ſervant labouring hard with his Highnes by the meanes of his friends to attaine to the place that was promiſed to him, the time being then veri fit and convenient for the performing thereof. At firſt he denied that euer he had promiſed any ſuch thing, hauing with time quite forgotten the mater: but in end his handwrit being produced, and the promiſe ſigned with his owne hand, hee confeſſed his fault freely, and immediatly without any delay cauſed him to be ſvvorne in the place, vvich he had promiſed to him.</p>
            <p>Hovvbeit this illuſtrious Prince in diuers particular actions did teſtifie both his great charitie and liberalitie, as tovvards the poore and indigent, tovvards his domeſticall ſeruants and others, and by contributing largelie tovvards the building
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3751:6"/>and reparation of Churches, and manie other vvorkes: yet I vvill only produce theſe three teſtimonies of his liberalitie.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, concerning that vvich he gave to a certaine ſtraunger a Frenchman by nation, vvho ſtiled himſelfe the Kings Profeſſor of the French tongue, and had indeed ſome little penſion of his Majeſtie for this ſame purpoſe. This Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, hauing crept into ſome favour vvith the Prince his Chamberleyne, prevailed vvith him ſo farre, that at laſt hee perſuaded him to ſpeake to his Highnes for him, that he might haue ſome litle penſion graunted to him, as he had of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie vvhich at firſt his H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>: vvould not graunt, ſaying, that he had nothing to do vvith him. Notvvitſtanding M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyne follovving cloſſe his ſute, and beſeeching him to take ſome pittie on him, ſith he vvas a ſtranger, and had but ſmall meanes to liue on, his H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>: at length anſvvered, ſaying; Hovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I am no vvayes bound to giue him any thing: yet to do you pleaſure, and becauſe he is a ſtranger and a Frenchman, I ſhall giue him vvhat you ſhall think fit; and vvithin a ſhort ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me after he gaue him ſuch a penſion, as pleaſed him verie vvell.</p>
            <p>The ſecond teſtimony is this; A good Poët, and right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, preſenting him a ſmall poëme, he receiued it verie graciouſlie, and vvilled a Gentleman that had his purſe, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtovv on him ſome token of his gracious acceptance; the Gentleman aſking him vvhether a couple of Iacobus vvould not ſerue. Fy for ſhame (ſaid his Highnes) give him at leaſt ten pieces.</p>
            <p>The third vvas, that ſome fevv vveekes before his ſicknes, conſidering vviſelie, that ſome of his cheef Gentlemen, vvhich vvere in eminent places, and neare to his perſon, had but ſmall meanes to maintaine the rank and place they vvere in, to cheriſh them in this their vvant, and make them goe on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3751:6"/>the more cheerfully in their ſeruice, and moreouer that they might not pretend that they were driuen through any neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be importune in begging of ſuch ſuits at his Highnes, as could not conveniently be graunted; he provided them with honeſt &amp; reaſonable penſions during their liues, and if he had lived a litle longer, intended to proceed further in this kinde of bounteous and provident liberality: but being prevented by untimely death, none of theſe worthy projects could take any effect. This is a notable example both of his liberality, and of his wary and Princely providence.</p>
            <p>He was exceeding magnifick and ſtately in all his doings, and principally in feaſting of great perſones, ſuch as was the young Duke of Brounſwick, the young Landgrave of Haſſe, the Duke of Wirtemberg and others, which he feaſted moſt royally, giuing them all maner of contentment, that they could haue deſired of him.</p>
            <p>And about ſome foure moneths before his death; at his houſe of <hi>Wootſtock</hi> he made ſuch a ſumptuous and great feaſt to the Kings Majeſtie his Father, that after his Majeſtie had conſidered &amp; vewed well the tables and meates ſet thereon, his Gentlemen and Servants richly apparelled and in good order, and all things in his houſe well ordered and gouerned, without any diſorder or confuſion, was ſo much amaſed at the ſight thereof, that he was forced to ſay, that he had neuer ſeen the like before all his lifetime, and that he could neuer doe ſo much in his owne houſe.</p>
            <p>Concerning his apparell, he loued to goe handſome and well cloathed: yet without any maner of ſuperfluity or exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. But as for his ſeruants and Gentlemen that were neare to his perſon, he was ſome what more curious, taking pleaſure to ſee them goe richly apparelled. Which he declared ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently by this example<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A certaine Gentleman, who had ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him a long time before, and with others was placed about
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3751:7"/>him in his minority by the Kings Majeſtie, being with the reſt of his houſhold Servants to be ſworne to him ouer againe at the taking up of his houſe (at which time he had free liberty to chuſe ſuch Seruants as pleaſed him beſt) he gaue way to the receauing of all the reſt, ſaue only this Gentleman, whom he forbade to ſweare, untill ſuch time as his Father had promiſed to apparrell him better in time comming; and as it was fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for his place. Which his Father hauing once promiſed to doe, at length after that all the reſt were ſworne, he gaue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der likewiſe to admit him to his place.</p>
            <p>He deſired alſo, to haue good attendance of his Seruants, and to be well ſerued, as it may appeare by this following. One of his Sewers comming one day a litle too late to wait, when his Highnes had already almoſt half dined, he was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by him, whence he came ſo late? He anſwered, that it was not yet eleuen of the clocke (ſaying ſo becauſe his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter dined commonly at that houre, and no ſooner.) The Prince anſwered him againe, that he would not be ſerued at an appointed houre only, but at all times.</p>
            <p>His modeſt diſpoſition, and naturall hating of vaine oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, began to ſhewe it ſelfe, when he was verie young. For being taught to handle the Pike, and his Teacher inſtructing him both by word and example to uſe an affected kind of ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telineſſe in marching and holding of his hand, he learned all other points of him ſoo well (as all men know:) but in no wayes would he frame himſelfe to that affected maner. And if ſometimes upon earneſt intreaty he did offer to uſe it, he would lanch at himſelfe, and preſently returne to his owne more modeſt and comelie maner.</p>
            <p>And whereas he had learned to daunce ſoo wel as none of his age being of a Princelie ranke or degree could doe it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: yet neuer tooke he much delight therein, nor offered himſelf to daunce, but was for the moſt part intreated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3751:7"/>The like modeſtie was ſeen in whatſoeuer he did or ſpake: yet was this his modeſtie no hinderance to his heroïcall and generous diſpoſition, which made him to performe all his exerciſes beſt, before moſt companie, and greateſt perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; as namely he neuer toſſed his Pyke better then in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Majeſtie and great Ambaſſadours, of whom was the Conſtable of Caſtile.</p>
            <p>From his generous mind it proceeded, that he delighted in handling of his armes, and in ſuch other manly and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall exerciſes: hence alſo did ariſe his affection to learning: wherein he ſo well profited, as I haue not heard of manie Princes of his age that could doe better. In quicke apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and memorie few of his age went beyond him: but none in judgement &amp; underſtanding of that which was taught him.</p>
            <p>When he beganne to haue ſome knowledge of the Latine tongue, being admoniſhed to chuſe himſelfe a Poſie out of ſundrie ſentences gathered by his ſcholemaiſter for this uſe, he read many that were good, but paſſed ouer them without chuſing till he came to this ſentence of <hi>Silius Italicus: Fax men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis honeſtae gloria, Renowne is a furtherer of an-honeſt mind:</hi> whereof himſelfe made choiſe. And to ſay the truth, none among them all did better fit him.</p>
            <p>The Kings Majeſtie aſking him, which were beſt verſes that he had learned in the firſt booke of Aeneides, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; Theſe,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rex erat Aenaeas nobis, quo juſtior alter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec pietate fuit, nec bello major &amp; armis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
In Engliſh;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We had a King Aeneas cald, a juſter was there none,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In vertue, or in faites of warre, or armes could match him one.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which indeed is a moſt excellent commendation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the three principall Vertues of a worthy Prince to Wit, Pietie, Iuſtice, and Valour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3751:8"/>Reading this vers; <hi>Tros Rutiluſve fuat nullo diſcrimine habebo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it Trojan or Italian he, no difference will I make.</hi> He ſayd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe would make uſe of the ſame, changing it thus; <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glus Scotuſve fuat nullo diſcrimine habebo. Be it English or Scot he, no differens will I make.</hi> In which change he reſpected the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable qualities of unpartiall judgement and affection, &amp; not the qualities of the verſe, which he knew to be erroneous.</p>
            <p>I come nowe to the rehearſall of ſundry of his pleaſant and witty ſpeaches, during his young and tender yeares, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the pregnancie of his witt, and vertuous diſpoſition doe appeare.</p>
            <p>When he was but a little paſt ſeaven yeares of age, a ſonne of the Earle of Marre, ſomething younger then himſelfe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out with one of his Pages, to whom (as his Highnes was informed) he had done ſome little wrong, he reproued him therefore, ſaying; I loue you, becauſe you are my Lords Sonne and my Kouſin: but if you be not better conditioned, I will loue ſuch a one better, naming the childe that complained of him.</p>
            <p>The firſt time that hee went out of the towne of Stirling to meet the King, ſeeing a little without the gate of the towne a ſtake of corne in proportion to a topp, wherewith he had wont to play, he ſaid to ſome that were with him; Loe there a goodly topp, whereupon one of them ſaying, why doe you not then play with it? He anſwered; ſett you it to me, and I will play with it.</p>
            <p>Being aſked very young what Inſtruments of Muſicke hee liked beſt, he anſwered, a Trumpet.</p>
            <p>On a time that he ſaw ſome hunting on a Deere, being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, whether he loved that hunting well? He anſwered; yes, but I loue another kinde of hunting better. One aſking him, what maner of hunting that was? hee anſwered; hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of theeues and rebelles with braue men and horſes. And
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3751:8"/>turning him to one of his Pages deſcended of Highland Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who were bruted to be theeues, he added; and ſuch theeues as I take ſhall be hanged, the great ones higher then the reſt, and you Sirra (if you bee a theefe) higheſt of all.</p>
            <p>Once in his childhood, in a merry humour taking up Straw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries with two ſpoones, when one might ſuffice, hee ſaid; the one I uſe as a Rappier, and the other as a Dagger.</p>
            <p>Being aſked of a Nobleman, whether after his Father hee had rather be King of England or Schotland? he demanded, whether of them was beſt? and anſwere being made, that it was England, then (ſaid he) would I haue both.</p>
            <p>A controverſy for ſport being ſtirred up by the King his Majeſty betwixt two, the one of whom, ſeruing him in good place by a nickname was called a Tailler, and loued very well his liquor, the other was knowne to bee a tall Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherman, they were both neare falling together by the eares, when as the Prince was willed by the King to make an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betweene them, which agreement, ſome that were by ſaid, muſt be written and ſealed by them: Whereunto the Prince anſwered; then muſt W. M. (this was he which hath the nickename of a taillor) ſeal it with chalke, for he can not write his name, and then I will agree them, upon condition that M. G. (this was the tall Trencherman) goe into the cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and drinke with W. M. and that W. M. make a cloakbag for M. G. to cary his victuals in.</p>
            <p>Eating in the Kings preſence a diſh of Milk, his Majeſty aſked him, why he eated ſo much childes meat? Sir, quot he, it is mans meate alſo. And immediatly after fed well of a Partrich, the King ſaid to him, that meate will make you a coward. Whereunto he anſwered, though it be a cowardly bird, yet it ſhall not make me a coward.</p>
            <p>The King aſking him whether hee loved Engliſhmen or Frenchmen better? hee anſwered, Engliſhmen. The King
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3751:9"/>demanded the cauſe thereof; becauſe, ſaid he, I am a kin to moe noble perſones of England, then of Fraunce, Then the King aſked him, whether he loued the Engliſh or the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes better, hee anſwered; the Engliſh. Whereunto the King replying, that his Mother was a German, hee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; Sir, you are the cauſe thereof.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time, his Majeſtie aſked him upon ſome men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of Queene Eliſabeth, whether ſhe had anie chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; he anſwered, hee underſtoode of none. And hath ſhe none (ſaid the King) that may bee called her ſonne? hee ſaid yes Sir, your ſelfe: and who nixt after me, ſaid his Majeſtie? Sir (ſaid he) your Sonne. Another ſtanding by, ſaying, that was Duke Charles: no (Sir) ſaid his Highnes, it muſt bee the eldeſt, wherein his diſcretion and modeſtie in not once naming himſelfe, is worth the noting.</p>
            <p>On a certaine time his Highnes wearing white ſhoes, one that reſorted ſometimes to him, ſaid, that he longed to kiſſe his feete: whereunto his Highnes anſwered; Sir, I am not the Pope. The other replying, that he would not kiſſe the Popes foote, unles it were to byte off his great too, his H<hi rend="sup">•</hi>: anſwered; if you were in Rome; you would be gladde to kiſſe his feete, without byting of his great too.</p>
            <p>Some one reporting to him, how the French King had ſaide, that as wel his Baſtard as the Baſtard of Normandie might conquere England: I will bee at eares with him (ſaid his Highnes) if he go about any ſuch matter.</p>
            <p>Some of his Seruants running to breake their faſte, and returning after a quicke diſpatch, being aſked what they had been doing, ſaid they: Wee were at our <hi>diſiune.</hi> One, who ſtood by, ſaid, that word is French, and that the right En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh was <hi>breakfaſt,</hi> it may ſo bee called indeede (ſaid his Highnes) for you breakefaſt to it.</p>
            <p>It being told him by ſome of his ſeruants in a houſe where
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3751:9"/>once he lay, how ſome of them had gone to bedd without their ſupper, through the fault of ſome pinching Officers of the houſe, he ſeemed at that inſtant to take no great notice: but the Lady of the houſe the nixt day comming to viſit him, whiles he was turning a booke that had manie pictures, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof one was of ſome that were painted ſitting at a feaſt, he ſaid to her; Madame, I inuite you to a feaſt. She ſmiling aſked him, Wat feaſt it was? he anſwered; to this feaſt. What (ſaid ſhe) to a painted feaſt? No better is that, ſaid he, which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in this houſe to ſome about mee. One, who was preſent, and had heard his Seruants complaine before: yet not gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing what he meaned aſked him if he underſtoode not that of ſome perſones figured in the Tapiſtrie of the Chamber, no (ſaid he) you know well enough who I meane.</p>
            <p>In Sir Thomas Sommerſet and Sir Henry Goodyeares pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence a litle before his iourney to England, the Earle of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſaid unto him; Sir, you heare how goodly and how rich a countrey England is: yet (Sir) conſidering that you haue been borne and brought up in Scotland, if I may be ſo bold, let me aſke you, which of both countreys you loue beſt? Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he anſwered; My Lord, after I haue been there a while I will tell you.</p>
            <p>One, who was fatt and corpulent, being by a Nobleman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to his Majeſtie for a good huntſman: yet (ſaid his Highnes ſtanding by) it ſeemeth thereby that he loueth Veniſon verie well.</p>
            <p>Whill he was telling a certaine Nobleman ſomething that he could haue done, but that his Schoolemaiſter was the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe why he did it not: one who had ſome credit about him, miſtaking what he ſaid, as if he would haue layde ſome fault committed by himſelfe upon his Tutor, ſaid to the Nobleman; It is the Prince his maner to lay his owne fault upon others. Hereat the Prince ſmyling taxed his impertinency, ſaying,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3751:10"/>Sir, indeed I might haue learned that leſſon of you.</p>
            <p>A certaine courtly and merrily conceipted Lady, who had a huſband, whom ſhee could not well enjoy in preſence of as pleaſant a conceipted Gentleman, who was then a widower, jeſting with his Highnes, requeſted him, that he would ſend her beyond Seas in ambaſſage, to court a certaine Prince his daughter for him. Marry, (ſaid his Highnes) I am contented ſo to doe, upon condition, that, when your huſband ſhall die you marry this Gentleman, who being well trauelled and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guaged, will ſerue you for a good guyde.</p>
            <p>His Schoolemaiſter to cheriſh his generous ſpirit, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renes in uttering his conceips, did giue him liberty of jeſting pleaſantly with himſelfe, offering him ſometimes occaſion thereof; as once when the Prince was plaing at the Shoufle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord, and in his play changed ſundry pieces, his Tutor being deſirous that euen in trifles he ſhould not be newfangled, ſaid to him, that he did ill to change ſo oft, and therevvith taking a piece in his hand, and ſaying that he vvould play vvell enough therevvith vvithout changing, threvv the piece on the boord: yet not ſo vvell, but that the Prince ſmyling, ſaid; vvell throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Maiſter. Whereupon Sir Adam Newton telling him, that he would not ſtriue with a Prince at ſhufleboord. He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; you Gownemen ſhould bee beſt at ſuch exerciſes: being not meet for thoſe that are more ſtirring. Yes, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Sir Adam Newton, I am fit for whipping of boyes. The Prince anſwered, you need not vaunt of that which a Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or Carman can do better then you. Yet can I doe more (ſaid Sir Adam Newton) I can governe fooliſh children. The Prince, reſpecting him euen in jeſting, came from the further end of the table, and ſmyling, ſaid, whileſt he paſſed by him; hee had need to be a wiſe man himſelfe that would doe that.</p>
            <p>At another time, playing at Gauffe (a play not unlike to Palemaille, whileſt his Schoolmaiſter ſtood by talking with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3751:10"/>another, and not marking his Highnes, warning him to ſtand further off, the Prince thinking he had gone aſide, lifted up his club to ſtrike the ball; In the meane time one ſtanding by, ſaid to him; Be ware (Sir) you bit not Sir <hi>Adam New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> Wherewith hee drawing backe his hand, ſaid; had I done ſo, I had but payed my debts.</p>
            <p>His Schoolemaiſter, hauing laid a wager with him, that he could not refraine from ſtanding with his backe to the fire, and ſeeing him forget himſelfe once or twice in ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding after that maner, ſaid to him, Sir, the wager is wonne; for you haue failed twiſe. Maiſter, anſwered his Highnes, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pieters Cocke did crow thriſe.</p>
            <p>Playing at Chitlecock with one farre taler then himſelfe, and hitting him by chanche with the Chitlecock on the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head; this is (ſaid his Highnes) the encounter of <hi>David</hi> with <hi>Golias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A young man, not very ſtaid or diſcreete himſelfe, taxed another, and ſaying, there was no man liuing more fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, Except your ſelfe (ſaid his Highnes.)</p>
            <p>Learning to play at the Violl of a very ſkilfull Muſitian, another not ſo ſkilfull, in his teachers preſence tooke on him to teach him ſundry points. His teacher ſaying, that already he had taught him. What (ſayeth his Highnes, jeaſting with him) will you not learne of your Maiſter? Hereat the other aſhamed, ſaid; Sir, I might rather learne of him. Then (ſaid his Highnes) he is ſufficient to teach me.</p>
            <p>One ſaid to him looking on a coffer painted on a wall, Sir, open that coffer, and beſtow ſome gift on me. Whereunto his Highnes anſwered; Finde you a keye to open it, and I will doe ſo.</p>
            <p>On a time as he was walking in the heate of the day, one told him, that the Sunne would ſcorce his face. To whom he anſwered; It is no matter, I am not a woman.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3751:11"/>Another telling him, that his face was already ſcorcht with the Sunne, put it then away from me (ſaid his Highnes.)</p>
            <p>A Seruant of his, having prepared himſelfe to waite on him, as he was to ride abroad with the King priuatly, his Highnes found fault with him for ſo doeing. Whereat the other taking the ſnuffe, and ſaying that he cared not for goe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad, his Highnes jeaſting at his impatience ſaid; I pray you good Sir, be not angry.</p>
            <p>To another of like humour, taking in euill part ſomewhat that he had ſaid to him, Sir, (ſaid his Highnes) you wlli take no exceptions againſt that I ſpeake.</p>
            <p>His Highnes as hee was ſhooting, aſking at a Gentleman that ſtood by, at what marck he ſhould ſhoote at. The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman ſaid, at a Welchman who was preſent. Will you ſee then (ſaid his Highnes) how I will ſhoote at a Welchman, and with theſe wordes he turned his backe to the Welchman, ſhooting his arrowe the cleane contrary way.</p>
            <p>A Welchman, who had taken a good carouſe in the Kings hearing, ſaying, that the Prince ſhould haue fourty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Welchmen to wayt on him againſt any King in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, the King aſking; what to doe? his Highnes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered merrily; to cut of the heades of 40000. leekes.</p>
            <p>A Preacher in his preſence preferring Cambridge before Oxford, the Prince aſked him, if he did not uſe in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to ſay, Cambridge and Oxford. Hee graunting that he did ſoo, his Highnes ſaid; But the firſt time I preach, I will ſay Oxford and Cambridge.</p>
            <p>The Kings Majeſty telling him, that he might not goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to hunting with him: becauſe the weather was very hoate and vnwholſome; Then will I take my Phyſitian with me, ſaid his Highnes.</p>
            <p>A merry Gentleman, who vvas ſaid to take his liquor ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry largely and kindly, giuing his Highnes to vnderſtand hovv
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3751:11"/>hee dranke oftimes to his health, ſaid merrily, that his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes had part of euery draught that he tooke. Then ſaid his Highnes, I muſt needes be euery day druncke.</p>
            <p>A number of young Gentlemen that daunced in his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes company, failing ſomewhat in the right meaſure of the daunce, and he who taught them ſaying; they would not proue good ſoldiours, unleſſe they keeped alwayes true or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and meaſure in marching. What then muſt they doe (ſaid his Highnes) when they paſſe thorow a ſwift running water?</p>
            <p>A ſkilfull Muſician, playing in his preſence, one aſked him, whether hee could play the ſame againe. Not (ſaid he) for the Kingdome of Spaine: for that were harder then for a Preacher to repeat word for word a Sermon that hee had not learned by root. A worthy Churchman, who ſtood by, ſaying, that hee thought a Preacher might doe that. Yea (ſaid his Highnes) for a Biſhoprick.</p>
            <p>One telling his Highnes, that ſome Haukes were to bee ſent him, but that he thought the King would intercept ſome of them. He may doe as pleaſeth him (ſaid his Highnes) for he ſhall not be put to his booke for the matter.</p>
            <p>A young jeaſter came out of Fraunce, telling his Highnes, that the French Kings daughter ſent him her heart. Haue you it then about you to giue me, (ſaid his High.) Note, that to this Ieaſter he ſpake in French.</p>
            <p>The ſame Ieaſter craued a fauour of his Highnes, and his Highnes, giuing him a boxe on the eare, perſiſted ſtill in his demand, whereupon his Highnes gaue him another very ſoundly. Then the jeaſter aſking him whether thoſe were his fauours. Yea (ſaid his Highnes) good enouch for ſuch as you are.</p>
            <p>Vnderſtanding hovv ſome of his Vnckle, the Duke of Holſteins men, behaved themſelues very ill, in forcing of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and wounding of ſome men to the danger of their liues,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3751:12"/>but that they were ſpared by the people, for that the ſaid Duke was the Queenes Brother, his Highnes ſaid; whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer other ſpared them, my Vncle himſelfe ſhould cauſe them to bee hanged.</p>
            <p>Some of the young Gentlemen about him, inuiting one another to looke on ſome faire Gentlewoman, that paſſed by, and ſaying to one that founde fault vvith them for ſo doeing, that it vvas no ſinne to looke on them, his Highnes ſaid; of looking commeth vvorſe, and the Scripture ſayeth;
<q>
                  <hi>Averte oculos tuos, ne videant vanitatem.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>A certaine Phyſician telling him on a time that he rode to take the ayre, that he did ride too faſt, he anſvvered; muſt I ride by rules of Phyſicke?</p>
            <p>The ſame man a litle after ſeeing a Beacon neare hand, and ſaying it vvas in Latine <hi>(Specula,)</hi> his Highnes lifting up from the ſadle his hinder part, and turning it tovvards him, ſaid; <hi>Hoc ſpeculum</hi> for you Maiſter Doctor.</p>
            <p>The Prince uſing in hott vveather to eate ſometimes of a colde Capon roſted the morning or evening before, one day that happened to be colder then the dayes immediately prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent had been, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doctor tolde him, that vvas no good meat for ſo cold vveather. Then ſee you M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doctor (ſaid he) that my cookes are no good Aſtronomers.</p>
            <p>The ſame Phyſician telling him at the ſame time, that it vvas unvvholſome for him to haue eaten hot meat &amp; colde meat together, I can not helpe that novv (ſaid his Highnes) though they ſhould both runne at tilt together in my belly.</p>
            <p>One of his Highnes Carvers by chance hauing cutt his Highnes finger, and ſucking out the blood thereof with his mouth, that it might heale the more eaſily, his Highnes being no wayes diſpleaſed with him therefore, ſaid to him in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant maner; If (which God forbid) my Father, I, and the reſt of his Iſſue, and kinred ſhould faile, you might claime
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3751:12"/>the Crowne; for you haue the blood Royall in you.</p>
            <p>His Highnes at a certaine play hauing choſen his young Gentlemen to play with him, and excluded his Seruants, it chanced that one of them well growne in yeares comming where they played, his Highnes called him to play with the young Gentlemen. Some that ſtood by aſking his Highnes why he admitted him rather then others; Becauſe (ſaid his Highnes) he may lawfully be of our number: for <hi>Bis pueri ſenes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kings Majeſtie upon ſome mention made of his youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt daughter Lady Marie, ſaying to the Prince that he had been once a girle (for ſuch indeede at the firſt the Midwife fained him to be) his Highnes ſaid to ſome that ſtood by; It was onlie <hi>vir, non Rex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the ſolemnitie of S. George, whilſt the noble Knights of the Garter ſtood in a rowe waſhing after ſupper, his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes being Lieutenant of the order, ſaid to ſome that ſtood by; Is it not ſtrange, that I ſhould be Lieutenant hauing 23. bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren all men?</p>
            <p>Some of his Highnes young Gentlemen, together with himſelfe, imitating in ſport the curvetting and high going of horſes, one that ſtood by, ſaid, they were like a companie of horſes. Which his Highnes noting, ſaid; Is it not better to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble a horſe, which is a courageous beaſt, then a dull and ſlow going Aſſe as you are?</p>
            <p>His Highnes ſaid to a fatt and corpulent Gentlewoman, who aſked of him ſome Veniſon, ſhould I giue you veniſon to make you fatter, that haue neede to be made leaner?</p>
            <p>His maner at the play at the Baſſe being to chooſe out of euerie couple one, repreſented by one of two things, and being aſked whether he would haue the white Roſe, or the red, he anſwered; I muſt haue them both; for they haue been ſo long and ſo well joyned together, as they muſt not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3751:13"/>At a ſolemne ſupper, a merry honeſt man of a ſwarfe and fat complexion, whom he called his page, whom he bid co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me neare to the table, and he ſaying that he durſt not come neare, leaſt he ſhould be taken for a diſh of meat, then muſt it be (ſaid his Highnes) for a gamond of bacon.</p>
            <p>A diſh of Gelee being ſet before his Highnes in forme of a crowne with three Lilies, the ſaid merry man ſaid to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that that diſh was worth a crowne. His Highnes anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; I would I had that crowne. The other replying that to be a great wiſh, how can it be great (ſaid his Highnes) when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you value it but at a crowne?</p>
            <p>The ſame man, looking at a picture ſomething laſciuiouſly made, and ſome ſaying that he bluſhed, others, that hee blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed not thereat, his Highnes jeaſting at his ſwarfe and grim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me face, ſaid to him; Pull off your viſard, that wee may ſee whether you bluſh or not.</p>
            <p>At Greenwich his Highnes miſſing at his table ſome meate that he fancied, and was wont to haue, and it being told him that the Officers ſaid; there vvas no more allowance thereof, he anſered; yet let them ſend me more, and let them ſet it on my head.</p>
            <p>Once in the ſame place, ſome telling his Highnes whilſt he vvas at dinner, hovv an undiſcreet Officer had refuſed to ſend him ſome fevv Cherries: becauſe (ſaid he) there vvas no more allovvance, then of thoſe vvhich vvere ſend him already, his Highnes, vvithout ſhovv of diſpleaſure, looking to a Trout that he had diſpoſed to eate of, and ſeeing no vineger on the table, aſked, is there no allowance of vineger neither?</p>
            <p>Some Abricots being ſent to him, he preſented them to the Kings Majeſty, who taſting of them, and ſaying they were not ripe, his Highnes anſwered; I can not mend that Sir, they grew not in my Garden.</p>
            <p>Maintaining the precedency of Oxford againſt a Doctor
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3751:13"/>of Cambridge, and the ſaid Doctor alleadging for the honor of Cambridge, that the King had thence great Stateſmen and Councellors, his Highnes anſwered; As you of Cambridge bragge of the Kings Councell and wiſdome, ſo can wee of Oxford of his Treaſure. Whereupon the Doctor aſking him, whether Treaſure were to be compared with Wiſdome? His Highnes anſwered him with another demaund, to wit, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had rather haue more wiſdome and learning, or a good benefice?</p>
            <p>His Phyſician telling him that it was unwholſome for him to eat colde meate, his Highnes anſwered; that he had a hot ſtomacke.</p>
            <p>His Schoolmaiſter willing to further him in other exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as well as learning, and for that cauſe uſing with him the practiſe of the Pike; on a time when he toſſed the ſame befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re his Highnes, failed inſome points. Whereat his Highnes telling him his faults, jeaſted with him, which his ſaid ſchool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter miſliking in ſome maner, ſaid; that it vvas an euill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. Maiſter, ſaid his Highnes: I take that humor of you. His Schoolemaiſter replying that it became not a Prince. Then doth it vvorſe become a Princes Schoolemaiſter, ſaid his Highnes.</p>
            <p>An old man ſome vvhat cholerick, vvho taught him to daunce, finding fault vvith him and other young Noblemen, for failing in the meaſures, and taxing them as careles boyes, his Highnes ſaid unto him; Remember, I pray you, that your ſelfe vvas once a boy.</p>
            <p>Hauing by chaunce cut his finger, and the ſame carver, vvho once cut it, and ſucked the blood thereof vvith his mouth, offering then to ſucke the ſame, ſome remembring the Prince his former jeaſt, aſked him, vvhat became of the blood Royall, that he hath already ſucked? and he anſvvered, that it vvas at his hart. It ſeemes ſo indeed (ſaid his Highnes)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3751:14"/>for it hath lately made you a Iuſtice of peace. Note, that a fevv dayes before hee came to that preferment.</p>
            <p>His Highnes once playing him after the maner of children, his Schoolmaiſter deſirous to dravv him to ſome more man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like exerciſe, amongſt other things ſaid unto him jeaſting; God ſend you a vviſe vvife, his Highnes added; that ſhee may gouerne you and me. His Scholemaiſter ſaying, that he had one of his ovvne, the Prince thereto anſvvered, But mine (if I had one) vvould gouerne your vvife, and by that meanes would gouerne both you and me.</p>
            <p>On a time for that he beſtovved not a fevv Plumbs that hee vvas eating, on ſome of his young noblemen, his tutor taxing him merrily, as not being liberall enough, Maiſter (ſaid his Highnes) vvhen you come to my houſe, you ſhall finde me liberall enough. Whereupon his Tutor ſaying, I had rather entertaine your Highnes at my houſe, if I had one, vvhereas novv I haue a vvife, and no houſe for her. His Highnes anſvve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that is not my fault.</p>
            <p>Mention being made of the mariage of ſome of his young Gentlemen, his Highnes ſaid, I vvould not be ſo ſoone ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and yet I vviſh to ſee my Father a grandfather.</p>
            <p>A Gentleman much delighted in the ſtudie and exerciſe of Poëſie, telling to his Highnes. ſome ſtrange and incredible things, another, vvho had been a Traueller ſaid, that hee vvould leaue the report of ſuch ſtrange vvonders to him that vvas a Traueller. Nay (ſaid his Highnes) this priuiledge is rather due to him vvho is a Poët.</p>
            <p>A Gentleman, taxing his Highnes ſomevvhat undiſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſome pleaſant and merry ſports and geſture, vvhich on a time he uſed, ſaid; that he reſembled a little Ape. And you (ſaid his Highnes) a great Baboun.</p>
            <p>The ſame man affirming eftſoons a thing, vvhich his Highnes vvith better reaſon denied, I yeeld to you (ſaid his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3751:14"/>Highnes) for it muſt bee as you will haue it.</p>
            <p>At another time, the ſame man going about in an angry mood to diſproue ſomewhat that his Highnes had ſpoken; Say what you liſt (ſayd his Highnes) I will not chalenge you to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate for the matter.</p>
            <p>On a time his Highnes ſhooting at Buttes, a Phiſitian tooke on him to teach him ſome rules of Archery, to whom his High. ſaying: that it became him better to giue precepts of Phyſicke then of Archery: another who ſtood by, commended him for a good Archer; Could you not then M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doctor (ſaid his H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:) hitt an urinall at the other Butt?</p>
            <p>A Gentleman, who hauing his haire cutt very ſhort had on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly left a tuffe of haire on his forehead, being aſked by ſome, why he kept that tuffe? It is (ſaid his Highnes) to the end that Mahomet may pull him up to Heaven thereby.</p>
            <p>The Marquis of S. German, aſking him whether he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be a hunting then at his Booke, his H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>: ſaid; he might well reſolue that doubt himſelfe: for he had once been of his age.</p>
            <p>As hee was toſſing a little rodd in manner of a Pike, his Schoolmaiſter to taxe him of trifling, ſaid in jeaſting manner, that Alexander the great, being of his age, uſed the ſame kind of exercice. And his Maiſter Ariſtotle (ſaid the Prince) had his beard trimmed after the ſame manner that yours is. Note, that the Barber had been with him the morning or euening before.</p>
            <p>One telling him of abuſes committed by ſome kinde of men, whereof he named but ſuch as were dead; You doe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſaid his Highnes, to name onely ſuch as are dead.</p>
            <p>Being told how one of his Seruants contrary to his direction had done ſomewhat, and a Gentleman going about to excuſe him, his H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>: ſaid; Eyther ſhall I be Maiſter, or he Maiſterles.</p>
            <p>Hauing deſired the Officers of his Houſe to furniſh plenty of wine and beere to a great number of his Seruants and others, that daunced and ſported them about a bonfire, at his Siſters
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3751:15"/>birth, and ſome good ſtore of pottes of wine and jacks of beere being brought forth, his Highnes thinking it to bee too little, ſaid: he would haue a Hogſhead of wine, and another of beere. The Officers making ſome difficulty thereat, and ſaying, there was enough, his Highnes compelled them to obey him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Whether am I Maiſter in mine owne houſe or you (Sirs?)</p>
            <p>A Gentleman his Seruant, who had been ſometimes a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, ſpeaking earneſtly and lowdly in excuſing ſome whom his High. would haue corrected for their faults, his H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>: ſaid to him; Remember (Sir) you are not now pleading at the Barre.</p>
            <p>One of his Seruants accuſtomed much to the wearing of ſcarfes, excuſing himſelfe that he might not play at Baſſe with his Highnes: by reaſon of a ſore legge. Why then, ſaid his Highnes, doe you not bind up your legge with a ſcarfe?</p>
            <p>It being the cuſtome of his Highnes and the young Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men about him to tell euery one an Hiſtory by turne, all of them deliuering ſome obſeruation upon the Hiſtorie told, one of them recounted how Papirius Curſor, a ſeuere and rigorous Commander among the Romanes, commaunded the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner to bring forth the axe, as it were to behead a certaine Captaine, for comming thorow feare too late to the field, and he looking for no other then preſent death, the ſaid Papirius hauing thus terrified him, ſaid to the executioner; Cutt up this roote, that it may not hinder our walking, and ſo laying a fine on the Captaine, diſmiſſed him. His Highnes being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his Schoolmaiſter to declare his obſeruation hereupon, ſaid; The Obſervation that I gather hence, is, that as Papirius was not ſo terrible as hee threatned, ſo will you not likewiſe be in keeping me all after noone at my book, as you haue threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to doe.</p>
            <p>He tooke great delight in ryding of great horſes, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to haue of the beſt and rareſt horſes that were to be found, and had ſuch care of them, that he went often to the ſtables to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3751:15"/>ſee them, and accounted them to be a part of his beſt Iewels, as on a time he declared euidently. For hauing ſent one of the beſt that he had, and which he loued dearly (named Pied-Admirall) to the Duke of Brounſwick his Couſin, who had been farre in loue with him during the time that he ſejourned in England, and one of his Seruants, who had gone ouer with the horſe to the Duke, hauing brought backe from him to his Highnes for a token a certaine booke full of pictures of horſes, with ſuch fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture as belonged to them; after that he had ſome what ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and as it were in diſdaine turned ouer ſome of the leaues the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof, he uttered this ſpeeches before the ſaid Seruant, and all that ſtood by; I would rather haue my Pied-Admirall againe aliue then all theſe painted beaſts.</p>
            <p>I had almoſt forgotten his Barriers, which I will heare ſet dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne after his witty and pleaſant ſpeeches.</p>
            <p>The ſixteenth yeare of his age, being come the time of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſtment in the Principality of Walles, and Cornuall, he did aduance his owne Title and Right, ſo farre as with modeſty he might: which preſently was gently and louingly entertained, and graunted of his Majeſty, with the conſent of the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable the high court of Parliament, the fourth of Iune follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, being appointed for that ſolemne action. The Chriſt maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe before which, his Highnes not only for his owne, recreation but alſo that the world might know what a braue Prince they were likely to enjoy, under the name of Meliades Lord of the Iſles (an ancient title due to the firſt borne of Scotland,) did in his name by ſome appointed for the ſame, of purpoſe ſtrangely attired, accompanied with Drummes and Trumpets in the Chamber of preſence, before the King and Queene, and in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the whole Court deliuer a challenge to all the Knights of Great Britaine in two ſpeeches, the relation whereof were out of purpoſe: but the ſumme was; That Meliades their noble Maiſter boyling withan earneſt deſire to try the valour of his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3751:16"/>young yeares in forraine countreys, and to know where Vertue and Valour Triumphed moſt, had ſent them abroad to eſpye the ſame, who after their long trauels in all countryes and returne, ſhewing how now here in any continent; ſaue in the fortunate Iſle of Great Britaine, they had found his wiſhes, which mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring mater of exceeding joy to their young Meliades, who as they ſaid, could lineally deriue his pedegree from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Kings of this Iſle) was the cauſe that he now ſent to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the firſt fruits of his chevalry at his Majeſtyes feet, thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter turning with a ſhort ſpeech to her Majeſtye, next to the Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, Lordes, and Knights, excuſing their Lord in this their ſhort and ſuddaine warning, and laſtly to the Ladies, they, after hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deliuery of their cartell, concerning time, place, conditions, number of weapons, and aſſaillaunts, tooke their leaue, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſolemnly as they entred. Now began euery where prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to be made for this great fight, and happy did he think himſelfe who ſhould be admitted as a defendant, much more aſſaillant. At laſt, to encounter his Highnes with his fix aſſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants 58. defendants conſiſting of Earles, Barons, Knights, and Eſquieres, were appointed and choſen 8. defendants to one aſſaillant; euery aſſaillant being to fight by turnes 8. ſpeciall ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, fighting twice euery time with puſh of Pike and Sword, twelue ſtroakes at a time, after which the barre for ſeparation was to be let downe untill a freſh on-ſet. The great night of this ſolemnity now approaching, his Highnes in his owne lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in the Chriſtmaſſe time, did feaſt all the Earles, Barons and Knights, aſſaillants and defendants, untill the great Twelfth appointed night, on vvhich this great fight vvas to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, vvhich being come, his Highnes, to the great vvonder of all the beholders, did admirably fight his part, giuing and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that night 32. puſhes of Pikes, and aboue 360. of ſtrookes with ſwordes, which is ſcarce credible in ſo young yeares, enough to aſſure the world that great Britaines braue HENRY aſp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to immortality.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3751:16"/>Againſt the morow after the ſaid fight, was alſo prouided a magnificke feaſt at his Highnes houſe of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames, at which their Majeſties, his Highnes Brother, and Siſter, with all other the Earles, Lords and Knights of the Court were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, where after ſupper (according as before they had been judged) his Highnes gaue three prizes to the three beſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, namely, to the right Honorable the Earle of Montgom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery one, and to Sir Thomas Darcy and Sir Robert Gordon Knights the other two.</p>
            <p>I will adde one Obſeruation more, drawne out of mine owne experience, that out of this one particular it may appeare in generall, what opinion our neighbour nations had of his H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>, and how much the greatnes of his name had anxiouſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed many of their mindes, which is this; I being in Fraunce about ſome 9. yeares agoe, and with others trauelling along the Riuer of Loire betwixt Orleans and Tours, there fortuned to bee in our companie a Gentleman of the citie of Bourdeaux, who upon ſome diſcours that we had together of Engliſh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, told me; that thoſe of that citie a little while before his Highnes his death, were mightily affrayed of ſome inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be made by him, hauing for a long time before toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the whole countrey of Gaſcony conceiued no ſmall jaelouſie and feare of his high and generous Spirit, the cauſe of this late feare being, for that the harueſt quarter (at which time the Engliſh and Scotiſh Shippes uſe to arriue there to prouide themſelues with wines) being then ſpent, and the winter ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon come already, and no Shippes arriuing as they had wont to doe, the more vigilant and wary ſort did verily ſuſpect that the ſea ports of England had been ſhutt vp, and all Shippes ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed for ſome great enterpriſe, which they could not thinke to be intended otherwiſe then againſt them, and that by the Prince his meanes only, as fearing no other. And moreouer, that at that time the citie was not prouided to indure a ſiege, chiefly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3751:17"/>through want of corne, which they could not prouide to any purpoſe without ſome time and leaſure; namely, ſince the ſame could not be effected without ſome ſhow of feare, which they were loath to ſhew openly, for diſcouraging of the citizens, and doubting that they might in end haue been laughed at, if it ſhould haue come to paſſe that they had miſtaken the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as it fell out indeed. For at lenth (though very late in the yeare) the Shippes ſo long expected, arriued after the accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med peaceable manner, ſome quantity of wheate was brought downe the ryver of Garumne by accident, and not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had certaine newes of his H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>: his death. All which things falling out almoſt together, did baniſh all feare out of their mindes, and ſuddainly filled their hearts with ioy, being rid of all danger through the death of the Prince. And the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Gentleman affirmed conſtantly, that, although they were exceeding glad to be thus deliuered from ſo great a feare, and to liue in peacable ſecurity, as they had wont to doe, yet on the other part they could not chuſe but be ſory for the loſſe of ſuch a braue and hopefull young Prince, who in his youthead had already become ſo famous and redoubted, and had made ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nations to admire him, and ſtand in feare of him.</p>
            <p>I might ſet downe many moe Obſeruations and proofes of all maner of Vertues, wherewith this Heroicall Prince was rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adorned, If I did not labour to eſhew prolixity, fearing that this Treatiſe might grow to bigge. To be ſhort, therefore I vvill only in fevv vvords adde, that; He vvas moſt vertuous all his lifetime, charitable and pittifull, familiar and gracious to all perſons; of fevv vvords, uſing grauity vvith ſuch as vvere graue, ſeuere in time and place, merry vvith thoſe that vvere ſo diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and vviſe in all his actions, farre aboue his age. He kept his houſhold Seruants in good order, and vvas very vigilant and carefull of all his affaires: His Court for Noble and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous behauiour did reſemble ſome colledge, that had been pikt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3751:17"/>and choſen out of the beſt and rareſt Spirits of great Britaine. He fauoured learning much. He made ſo much of Soldiours &amp; men of vvarre, that he made diuers Captaines Gentlemen of his priuy Chamber, and tooke great pleaſure in theyr company, diſcourſing vvith them often touching military diſcipline. He admired great and rare Spirits, yea euen thoſe of mechanicall and meane perſons, retaining diuers of that ſort, and vvent ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to ſee them vvork in their trades.</p>
            <p>He delighted much in Architecture and building, &amp; had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made ſome beginning thereof at Richmond houſe; And doubtleſſe, if God had prolonged his dayes, he had cauſed build many curious and ſumptuons buildings. Out of his Heroicall mind, which breathed nothing but noble deedes, he adorned likewiſe the Britiſh Ocean with that ſtately Prince, a fit name for ſuch a goodly Ship, being as it were a Prince compared wieh other veſſels. Hee loued Muſicke, and namely good conſorts of Inſtruments and voices ioyned together. In his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily exerciſes he did not exceede the limits of lawfull mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. He loued the Tinniſh well. He tooke no delight in pleaſants and jeaſters, neither yet was he caried away with any affection to ſtage-playes. He delighted more in hauking then hunting. He was tall and of an high ſtature, his body was ſtrong and well proportioned, his ſhoulders were broad, his eyes quicke and pleaſant, his forehead broad, his noſe bigg, his chinne broad and clouen, his haire inclining to bleeke, whereas before it had been of a whitiſh colour, the colour of his face ſome what ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe and ſcorched with the ſunne, his whole face and viſage co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely and beautifull, looking for the moſt part with a ſweete, ſmyling, and amiable countenance, and withall full of grauity, and Princely majeſty, reſembling much in the ſhape of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and diuers actions the King of Dennemark his Vncle. So that being thus beautified and adorned with ſo many excellent gifts, and moſt rare vertues both of ſoule and body, he did draw
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3751:18"/>not only the eyes of many to come and behold him, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe did eaſily gaine the hearts of all men, yea euen of thoſe, which had only heard of him. This illuſtrious and mighty Prince increaſſing thus in ſtrenght, honor, and wiſdome, withall maner of vertues, being the hope and ſolace of the people, the glorie of his Parents, cheriſſed and loued of all men, euen of ſtraungers and thoſe of forreine nations, and thinking on no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then ſuch a ſuddaine and unexpected change, as fell out ſoone after, this moſt worthy perſonage (farre otherway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es then his tender yeares and age ſeemed to promiſe to us) by the will of his ſupreme creator was ſeaſed with a heauy diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and within a few dayes after was a tached by death ſelfe, it ſo pleaſing the almighty God, to take from this world up to himſelfe this noble Soule, with ſuch piety and deuotion, as could be wiſhed in a Chriſtian ſoule: to the intent that he might place him in one of his coeleſtiall manſions, and ſo obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne euerlaſting life. Which happened about eight of the clocke at night, on Friday the 6. of Nouember, 1612.</p>
            <p>This terrible and fearfull ecclipſe not hauing been foretold and prognoſticated long before, did moue and trouble each one by diuers maners, ſeeing cleerly herein the unrecoverable loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, wherewith God puniſhed us, by taking away this Prince from the earth, from the King his Father, the cheefe ſtaffe of his old age, and from the people their moſt certaine hope; which they had, to ſe renewed one day in this illuſtrions graffe all the noble vertues of his forefathers. The dolefull and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cries of all the people were great euery where, their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines turned into heauines, and their laughing into floods of teares, bewailing and lamenting dayly this great and unfortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſtroke, whereof the vvound yet ſtill bleedeth. God, of his vvonted mercy, bleſſe and preſerue our moſt noble King CHAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LES, and the reſt of this Royall family, vvithout kindling his vvrath any more againſt us, by inflicting on us the heauy and due puniſhment, vvhich our ſinnes haue deſerued.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:3751:18"/>
            <head>THE RELATION <hi>OF THE</hi> Sicknes and Death of the moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous HENRY, Prince of Walles, &amp;c. TOGETHER <hi>With the opening of his Body.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>RINCE HENRY in the nineteenth yeare of his age, being naturally very hott, accuſtomed to bleede very oftentimes at the noſe aboundantly, yea and without exerciſe, but much more after any violent exerciſing of the body; this naturall excretion hauing been ſtopt theſe three monethis bypaſt; the laſt ſummer of this yeare 1612. (being exceſſiue in degree &amp; continuance of heat, more then any that now liue in England had euer ſeene) hauing conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually wearied his body with extreme exercices, and mouing at hunting, in the heat of the day, with riding, with playing at tinniſh, and conſequently hauing oftentimes chafed his blood after an extraordinary maner (which hauing been ſtirred in the morning, was accuſtomed not to ſetle againe all the day long.) And moreouer, hauing eaten fruit ſome what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiuely, chiefly Melons and Grapes that were not fully ripe: hauing often filled himſelfe with fiſh, and with Oyſters both raw and dreſſed with fire, at euery meale, three or foure dayes in the weeke; finally, to coole the burning heat that troubled
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3751:19"/>his body in the Summer, hauing as often as occaſion would ſerue, w. ſhed himſelfe in the ryver, after ſupper, with a full ſtomack, remaining in the water for ſome houres together. After all theſe diſorders, in end hee fell ſicke at <hi>Richmond,</hi> the tenth day of October, 1612. The two next dayes after, he had two fits with ſhivering and heat, without any ſweat follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing after. Which being perceiued by his ordinary Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, he hauing ordained and cauſed to giue him an ordinary remollitive glyſter ſimply, without any looſing medicine, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a gentle operation, the humors hauing been ſtirred, which were in great quantity, in this full body, upon the morow after he had 25. ſtooles, and there came from him a great quantity of rotten and ſtinking choler, and at the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end ſome flegme. The voyding hereof did good: but the roote remaining faſt, and the body being toyled with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe, and laſſitudes, and with an interrupted and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſleepe, his Highnes his Phyſician thought it good to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge him with the pills, which he was accuſtomed to giue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meales, which wrought foure or fiue litle times weakly with great aſſwaging. Neuertheleſſe after a few dayes, the diſeaſe increaſing by litle and litle, and nature yeelding to the cauſes of the diſeaſe (although his Highnes did ſtriue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his paine, labouring to couer the ſame, and ſhake it off) upon the fifth day after the firſt beginning of his ſickly diſpoſition, which was on Sunday the 25. of October, his Highnes hauing founde himſelfe very ill the Saturday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (though hee had played at Tinniſh) and farre worſe on Sunday morning, his face being pale and parched with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, his eyes hollow and of a wanne colour, being at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi> about three of the clocke after noone, fell in a light ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (an accident very common to him and many of his ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3751:19"/>which was followed by a light ſhivering, and with a heat; with great paine of the head, which had laſted many dayes, yea and with whirlings and giddineſſe, chiefly when he went about to riſe out of his bed. At laſt his Highnes had a fit of a feuer. Whereupon the Kings Majeſty hauing ſent to him Doctor <hi>Mayerne,</hi> his chiefe Phyſician, hee being come to his Highnes at eight of the clocke at night, found his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in a feauer, with a red viſage, with troubled eyes, that could not indure the light of the candle, his lippes blacke, his tongue drie, and an extreme thirſt to drinke, which hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes exceedingly tormented his Highnes ſo long as his braine was free and able to feele his paine. For this time the Doctor was content to ordaine a cordiall and refreſhing pti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſane, to quench the thirſt, and a broth to be taken at the end of the fit. Vpon the next day came together Doctor <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> ordinary Phyſician to his Highnes, and Doctor <hi>Mayer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> the foreſaid Phyſician to the King, ſent by his Majeſty, who hauing conſidered that his Highnes had had a moſt reſtles night (as the preceeding five or ſix had been) and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to haue the ſame thirſt and drienes which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, together with a ſtarting of the ſinue partes, and the belly bent; and the urines crude and white, and coſtiveneſſe, with common conſent they ordained a lenitive glyſter for him, which cauſed him to voyd gently three or foure times ſome very ſtinking yelow choler. All that day long his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes was without any feauer, roſe and played after dinner with the Duke of York, hauing alwayes notwithſtanding a moſt pitifull countenance, and drienes in the mouth, with ſome great alteration; for which cauſe they ordained cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall ulleps that were tart and cooling, and (to preuent all dangers) forgot not to miniſter ſome Behezar, Vnicornes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3751:20"/>horne, and ſuch like antidotes. All his brothers were made according to the ſame intention, and all the reſt of his diet was to the ſame end. The next night, after the accuſtomed maner, affoorded him no reſt, whith the drouth, which one laboured to quench with the foreſaid Iuleps. The next day about noonetide the fit returned with cold, and great heate, which increaſed with greater meaſure of all its former ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, till eight of the clock: at nine, the feuer decreaſed, and after ten ceaſed altogether. The morning following his Highnes ſleept quietly enough. In the meane time were heard great noyſes in his belly, whereof the fore part and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des about the ſhort ribs and aboue the nauill, were bent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re then ordinary. Which being conſidered, the foreſaid Doctors hauing all that day ſtriuen with cordials, reckoning the beginning of the diſeaſe to haue been from the Prince his being at <hi>Richmond,</hi> and not only from the Sunday; wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghing the profit which his Highnes had receiued by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions, as well naturall as artificiall, that had paſt before, and looking to the maner of liuing, and the great fulnes of putrified humours, that were in the naturall partes, which hauing been kindled had cauſed a feuer, which followed the nature of a Tertian (though venemous becauſe of its no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table putrefaction, and ready to turne to a continuall feuer, for the quantity of the mater, as it came to paſſe afterward) the foreſaid Phyſicians (I ſay) aduiſed upon a light purgation, which were able only to diminiſh the quantity of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, judging the ſame to be ſo much the more neceſſary then the laſt Glyſter; and the ſtirring noyſes heard in the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did inuite one to ſolace nature by that part. Thereupon his Highnes was deſired by the foreſaid Doctors to call a Councell of Phyſicians, to conſult and aduiſe more largely
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3751:20"/>of this buſines, which he flatly refuſed, as being unwilling to haue many Phyſicians, as thoſe that came afterward might gather by his countenance, and the King his ſelfe can witnes. So not to ſpend the next day following without doing that which was moſt neceſſary; his Highnes being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together without any feuer, there was giuen to him a gentle medicine of boiled Sene, and Rhubarbe infuſed in cordiall and cooling liquours, with ſome Syrupe Roſate looſing. This medicine wrought with incredible paine, ſeauen or eight times, and brought away great ſtore of putrified cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and towards the end ſome putrified flegme. From that day forth the urines beganne to change, and to thicken, and to ſhew ſome litle cloude, which betokened concoction. The night was troubleſome after the accuſtomed maner, ſaue in the morning. His breath which was alwayes ſhort became more eaſy and longer, the paine of the head leſſe. Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings of the eares that continued (though unequally) from the beginning to the end; the ſtartings being alike. In this caſe the Iuleps with the Behezar, Vnicornes horne, pearles, and bone of the Stagges heart, &amp;c. were continued. Vpon the next the fit came with a light cooling, which ſince that time was not felt, and from that houre forth, the feuer hath been alwayes continuall, with notable remiſſions or brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, and very unequall redoublings euery day; the one great, the other leſſe. In the courſe of this continuall feuer the tongue became blacke, the drouth, the ſtartings and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings did increaſe. At ths end of the fifth day nature ſtrained it ſelfe to voyd ſome thing by the belly, but litle, the urines did nowayes ſhew the greatnes of the danger. Doctor <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> was called aſide from the reſt, vvho counſelled only to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter internall and externall cordials, analeptickes, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3751:21"/>the diet that vvas preſcribed, and his adviſe vvas fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved. The night vvas very reſtles, and the morning, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes, ſome vvhat more gentle. Vpon the ſixth the entral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les hauing been vvaſhed vvith fruit by a Glyſter in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, about three of the clock after noone came the leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubling, during vvhich the face vvas very red, the breath ſhort, the pulſe full of ſvviftneſſe. In the fitt the noſe fell a bleeding, but after the voyding of tvvo ounces of blood cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, not vvithout ſome eaſing. This bleeding ſhevved it ſelfe (though in ſmaller quantity) the ſeauenth and eight day; from that houre forth a motion vvas made of letting blood, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto nature by this attempt did invite in a feuer, moreouer continuall, in an extreme fulneſſe, in a temperature exceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely hott, in a ſubject accuſtomed to bleed at the noſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his benefite theſe many moneths bypaſt. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles the ſeauenth paſt ouer, and the greater part of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians vvas of the opinion, that it vvas expedient to vvaite till the <hi>Criſis</hi> vvere come, though the diſeaſe vvas crude; and that there vvas no appearance at all thereof: Thus upon this day came the great redoubling, vvith rauing, and that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing avvake: blackneſſe, drieneſſe, and roughneſſe of the ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, vvith ulceration of the throat; the ſingings and ſtartings vvere vvaxed greater, the urines more crude, and there vvas vvithall a fearfull unquietnes, vvhich continued the vvhole night. The increaſing of the euill, and nature beginning to bovv and relent, made the letting of blood to be motioned more earneſtly then before, as being the only remedy to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his Highnes, if the ſame vvere let in a juſt quantity, yea and by reiterating the ſame if need vvere, as all maner of like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhoods did ſhevv, in regarde of the conſtitution of the body, the age, the ſtrength, and other accidents. After a very great
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3751:21"/>debate, in end the three Doctors <hi>Mayerne, Hammon,</hi> and <hi>Butler,</hi> agreed together, the eight day after that his Highnes had taken his bed, and in their preſence vvas dravven from the Median or middle vaine of the right arme ſome 7. or 8. oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of blood. His H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>: ſuffered the ſame vvith courage, deſired them to dravv ſome more, vvas nothing vveakened thereby, the blood came running like a ſtreame, and almoſt immediatly thereafter he felt ſome comfort. The blood, after that it vvas become cold, vvas ſeene by any vvhoſoeuer deſired to ſee it, all putrified, blevv on the upper part, and almoſt vvithout any ſmall ſtringes, not fully thickened. His Highnes all the time of his ſicknes neuer found himſelfe ſo vvell as that day, and had no redoubling, in ſuch ſort that it ſeemed by his pulſe, that the feuer vvould haue left him.</p>
            <p>The ſingins of the eares and the ſtartings were diminiſhed, the night become better, though with litle reſt; the urines and excrements better concocted, the drouth ſomewhat aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaged, and his eyes beganne to indure the light better. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ninth, the great redoubling came with leſſe heate then had done the ſeauenth day. In this fit, the breath became ſhorter; the pulſe beating more frequently, the face redder, the tongue blacker, and the drouth greater, the ſtartings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and the drouſines began: breefly, all that appeared, which was able to make it appeare, that the blood and the humours had with aboundance and violence caſt themſelues upward toward the braine. This night his Highnes raued much more then before, uſing ſom diſcourſes out of purpoſe, he caſt himſelfe out of the bedde, called for his clothes, and ſpake of going away. In the morning of this day Doctor <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> was ſent by the King to the Prince, who tooke his comming impatiently, untill ſuch time as he had been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3751:22"/>by the other ordinary Phyſicians; that hee had need to be ſuccoured with all maner of good counſell, and that the number of learned men could not chuſe but bee very health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and fit for recouering of his Highnes his health. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Atkins</hi> told before the King and the Lordes of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, that this diſeaſe was a putride feuer, whereof the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing heat wat under the liuer, in the firſt paſſages, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the malignity that accompanied it to proceed of putrefaction, which being come to the higheſt degree ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the nature of poiſon. Vpon the tenth, all the accidents were increaſed; and the ſtartings turning into convulſions, the rauing hauing become greater, and the drouſines more troubleſome, with the feuer, which was euer more violent toward the euening, and all the reſt of the euils, in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a motion vvas made to let blood, the vvhich being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allovved by the greater part, ſtrong cordials vvere uſed, &amp; a Glyſter; by the vvhich much putrified and ſtinking matter hauing been brought forth, his High. did caſt up the ſtones of the grapes vvhich he had eaten ten or tvvelfe dayes before. All vvas vvithout effect; and the night of that day his High. beganne (the feuer being increaſed) to raue more then euer he did, to caſt himſelfe to and fro, to leape out of the bed; to ſing in his ſleepe, and pull the ſheets together to him. The convulſions (vvhich vvith the rauing vvere foretold from the fifth day of the diſeaſe (became more violent; the tongue, though dry and blacke with the whole throat did not moue his Highnes to call for drinke, an euident ſigne that the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion place of reaſon and underſtanding did ſuffer extremely. In end, all the eleuenth day, euery thing became vvorſe and vvorſe (ſaue ſome litle breathing) and the greater part of the Phyſicians did thinke it expedient to vvaite for the <hi>Criſes,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:3751:22"/>which were farre of, and appeared nowayes. In the night of the tenth day, cupping glaſſes with ſcarification were applied to the ſhoulders; and pigeons to the head being ſhauen. The eleuenth, a Cock clouen along through the back was applied, and the cordials were multiplied in number and in quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, all without any fruit. Then the danger appeared to be certaine, which had been foretold long ago. The which to withſtand and helpe, ſo farre as art would permit, and the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the diſeaſe ſeemed to require, upon the twelfth morning the letting of blood was againe debated among the Doctors, <hi>Mayerne, Hammon, Atkins,</hi> and <hi>Butler;</hi> one of them alleadging, that the blood had caſt it ſelfe upward violently, and by filling of the braine, did through its venemous ſharpnes, and quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, cauſe the rauing and convulſions, yet without paine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſpirit was troubled, which accidents did caſt his H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>: into eminent danger, more then the drouſines, the cauſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof was in the ventricles, like as the foreſaid hott and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick blood was in the caules or thinne ſkinnes, and that conſequently there was no other preſent remedie, but to open a veine; which his ſtrength ſeemed not to withſtand, ſince the pulſe was ſtrong enough, and his Highnes did riſe to go to his ſtoole, remaining at the ſame without any weaknes, which had not happened to him ſince the beginning of his ſicknes. The reſt of the Phyſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s miſliked this aduiſe, thought it good to continue, to double and triple the cordials, and to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion of the humour from the braine with a Glyſter, which wrought very well, but without any other effect, ſaue that his Highnes after voyding, came to himſelfe, and with judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and underſtanding gaue eare to the exhortations, and prayers of the Lord Arch-biſhop of Canturberry, ſhewing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3751:23"/>ſignes of piety, and contempt of this world, and a great contentment to prepare himſelfe to goe and poſſeſſe eternall reſt. After this he ſleept quietly enough, ſome three houres, the convulſions and rauings being diminiſhed. Toward the euening beſides the foreſaid Doctors, the Doctors <hi>Gifford</hi> and <hi>Palmer</hi> were brought in. They went all to a conſultation together, whereat ſome of them hauing remarked ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in this diſeaſe (although none of all thoſe that had ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. breath a thouſand times, and watched continually neare unto him had euer found themſelues ill, and that more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer throughout his whole diſeaſe he had neuer any ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes at the heart or vomiting, or any ſpott of purples, or other tokens on his body the others hauing denied the ſame flatly, and the great neceſſity of letting blood hauing been declared, whereof the opportunity was paſt for that time, by reaſon of the excretion of the belly, in end, by the plurality of voices the Diaſcordium was concluded, in preſence of Sir <hi>Thomas Challoner</hi> Knight, Chamberlayne to his Highnes, who among others a moſt worthy Seruant of his Maiſter, was continually with him, and was at the greateſt part of the conſultations, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Sir <hi>David Murray</hi> Knight, firſt Gentleman of the Bed-chamber, and Maiſter of the Robbes and Wardrobe, whoſe faithfulneſſe and diligent care is knowen to euery one. The relation of the foreſaid conſultations ſet downe in this treatiſe, may be controlled by theſe two perſons of honour and dignity, or be confirmed by their voices: and by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all his Highnes his Gentlemen, that were witneſſes of all things. According to the reſolution taken, at ten of the clock at night, or there about, was miniſtered the Diaſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, tempered with cordials which were not very hott. The
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3751:23"/>operation hereof was ſmall, and his Highnes reſted with his ordinary accidents, though aſſwaged neuer ſo litle. After the ſpace of four houres, the backe-bone, the ſhoulders, and the armes, with the tongue, ſuffered diuers convulſions. The ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing increaſed, the muſcle Sphincter loſing its naturall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, did ſuffer ſome untimely excretion to come forth, and death ſeemed to be very neare hand. In this deſperate caſe euery one haſted to hinder this unſpeakable loſſe, and out of the abundance of their affection, propounded that, which they thought might do any good. The Doctors (after that they had giuen out their prognoſtick, which they perceiued would proue but too true) hauing neuer preaſſed to giue his Highnes any thing whatſoeuer, but ſuch whereof they knew the preparation, or making. In end, by the common conſent of all ſix, was giuen to his Highnes a cordiall, which had its effect, by aſſwaging the rauings and convulſions, and cauſing him ſweat abundantly, which was the firſt time that he had ſweat any. But all in vaine, in ſuch ſort that this moſt illuſtrious Prince, hauing receiued no comfort by this excretion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in all its qualities; the Councell of Phyſicians per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing nature to be vanquiſhed, and that art was unable to attaine to affoord ſufficient helpe unto the ſame, committed the reſt into the hands of God, whom it pleaſed a litle after, to take from the world this moſt noble &amp; heroicall ſoule up to himſelfe, that he might inherit with his Sauiour Chriſt a perfect and permanent felicity. This happened about eight of the clock at night, upon Friday the 6. of Nouember, 1612.</p>
            <p>VPon the next day after the death, which was on Saturday the ſeauenth of the foreſaid moneth, by his Majeſties co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3751:24"/>and order from the Lordes of the Councell, about 5. of the clocke at night, all the Phyſicians that had been at his cure, the Prince Elector Palatine his Phyſician, and others, the Gentlemen of the late Prince his Chambers, and others his Seruants, aſſembled together in the ſame chamber where he died, where ſuch were admitted, as it pleaſed to be preſent there without confuſion indifferently, in preſence of the whole aſſembly his body was opened, by the Kings and his Highnes his Surgeons, which in its outward and inward parts was found to be ſuch as followes.</p>
            <p>THe Skinne (as of one that is dead) pale, nowayes ſpotted with blacke, or blew, or lead colour, which might breed ſuſpicion of any violence, farre leſſe marked with purples, like fleabits, which might argue any peſtilent or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagious poiſon. About the Kidneys, buttocks, and hinder parts of the thighes full of redneſſe, by reaſon of lying for a long time on the bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, with great paine and labour. The belly ſomewhat ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and ſtretched out through windineſſe which iſſued forth by the leaſt opening, that was made of the nauill (being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally lifted up) and immediatly the belly fell downe. The Stomach whole and ſound without and within, hauing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer been troubled during the whole ſicknes, nor ſuffered any will to vomite, vomitings, hickots, nor any other accident, which might giue euidence, that it had receiued any ſecret wrong. The <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iuer without, in its higher or upper part mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with points; in the lower with blakiſh lines, and farre p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ler and wanner, then it ſhould haue been. The Gall-blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der voide of humour, full of wind. The Splene aboue, and in its low extremity ſomewhat blacke, filled with a blacke
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3751:24"/>and earthly blood. The Kidneis very goodly, and without blemiſh. The Midriffe beneath the parts about the heart (which had too litle mater in them) ſpotted with blacke, and as it were a leaden black and blew colour. The Lungs almoſt all blacke, in the greateſt part thereof, the reſt being marked with blacke, puft up and full of a parched blood, and of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt bloody ſeroſity, which foaming iſſued forth plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at a part of the body of the lungs that was opened. In which opening and cutting the parts about to ſhew the heart, the Surgeon through miſchance hauing cut the thrunke of the great veine, the greateſt part of the blood emptied it ſelfe into the Thorax, leauing the lower veines empty, whereof the company was preſently aduertiſed. From this colour and framing of the lungs, were gathered ſome conſequences of an exceeding great fulneſſe, and of an exceſſiue heat, which appeared yet more, in ſo farre as the vvindpipe, the throat, and the tongue vvere ſmeared ouer vvith a blacke ſewet and among other accidents, the tongue drie and chinked in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places. The Heart goodly, whole in appearance, and without any fault that could be remarked, in any of its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. The hindmoſt veines, which are in the inner cauſe of the braine (called Pious mother) ſwelled and puft up through the abundance of blood, farre beyond the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall order. The ſubſtance of the Braine very goodly and cleane: but the venticles thereof full of a very cleare water, which came forth in great plenty at the cutting. One part of theſe accidents was engendered by the feuer (venemous only becauſe of the putrifaction of the ſame) of diuers hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours gathered together a long time before, his Highnes not being ſubject to any dangerous diſeaſe, either by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3751:25"/>or birth. Another part by reaſon of the convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ravings, and drouſines, which through fulneſſe, cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the naturall heate, and extinguiſhing the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of life through naughtineſſe, haue brought his Highnes to his graue, without any appearance, ſigne, or accident of poiſon.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of this Relation hauing been penned in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of all the foreſaid Phyſicians, by one of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, was ſent to his Majeſty, ſubſcribed by them all, the day after the opening of the body.</p>
            <trailer>SIC TRANSIT GLORIA MVNDI.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
